Guide to the Allegheny Observatory Records, 1850-1977 UA.5.1
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Correspondence of Directors/Acting Directors, 1850-1977; I.
  - Frank Schlesinger, 1899-1920, 1907; 6.
    - Correspondence from AIS/Yale University Project
      - White, James F. (Publishers)
      - White, Jesse (University of Pittsburgh)
      - White, Scott A.
      - White, William Charles (University of Pittsburgh)
      - Whitney, Mary (Box 17j, Folder 21)
      - Whitney, W.R.
      - Whittmer, Clara
      - Whyte, Charles (United Free Church)
      - Wicks, Mark (Thorton Heath)
      - Wilkins, Mary (Box 17j, Folder 22)
      - Willard, Elisa (Carnegie Library)
      - Willard, Storage Battery Co.
      - Williamson, Robert (Madison Wisconsin)
      - Wilsing, F.
      - Wilson, D.J. (Case School of Applied Science) (Box 17j, Folder 23)
      - Wilson, E.B. (National Academy of Sciences)
      - Wilson, Herbert C. (Carleton College)
      - H.W. Wilson Co.
      - Wilson, Ralph (Goodsell Observatory - Carleton College)
      - Windsor, William (Box 17j, Folder 24)
      - Winters, Edna (Indiana Normal School)
      - Wirth, Andrew G.
      - Witmer, Samuel
      - Wittig, Gustav (University of Alabama)
      - Wolf, Max (Box 17j, Folder 25)
      - Womer, P.P.(Washburn College)
      - Wood, Harry O. (National Research Council)
      - Wood, R.W. (Johns Hopkins University)
      - Woods, Harry I. (Washburn College)
      - Woodward, R.S. (Carnegie Institute of Washington) (Box 17j, Folder 26)
      - Woodwell, Joseph F. (Box 17j, Folder 27)
      - Worth, S.D. (Dept. of Commerce and Labor)
      - Wrightson, E.H. (Allegheny Loan and Trust Co.)
      - Yale University (Box 17j, Folder 28)
      - YMCA
      - Young, Anne (Mt. Holyoke College)
      - Young, Charles Augustus (Princeton)
      - Young, R.K. (Dept. of Interior) (Box 17j, Folder 29)
      - Young, S. Edward (Second Presbyterian Church)
      - Ziss, Carl (Box 17j, Folder 30)
      - Zenith Stove and Heater Co.
      - Zenthess, H.G. (Videnskabernes Selskab)
      - Observatory of Zi-Ka-wes
      - Zwillinger, Max (Crown Optical Co.)
    - Addendum - Personal Correspondence
      - Aitken, Robert G. (Lick Observatory, Hamilton, CA), September 6, 1901; June 5, 1902 (Box 17j, Folder 31)
      - Albrecht, Theodore, January 4, 1900
      - Arnand, Joseph J. (New York), March 26, 1900; March 24, 1901
      - Barnard, Edward E. (Yerkes Observatory), April 16, 1900; February 14, 1901
      - Barrett, S.B. (Yerkes Observatory), January 13, 1903-March 31, 1903
      - Bauer, George N. (New York), January 4, 1900
      - Burkhalter, Charles (Cabot Observatory), March 17, 1900
      - Campbell, William W. (Lick Observatory), August 21, 1900-March 11, 1903 (Box 17j, Folder 32)
      - Chase, F.L. (Boulder, CO), June 16, 1903; June 22, 1903
      - Chester, C.W. (Naval Observatory), April 3, 1903
      - Davis, Herman (Gaithersburg, MD), February 11, 1900-January 3, 1903
      - Davroton E. (San Francisco), March 13, 1900; March 20, 1900
      - Edwards, Frank V. (US Coast and Geodetic Survey), May 2, 1900; November 7, 1900 (Box 17j, Folder 33)
      - Ehrenberg, Frederick (New York), June 27, 1900
      - Ellerman, Ferdinand (Yerkes Observatory, Williams Bay, WI), March 13, 1900; March 20, 1900
      - Gildein, Otto von (San Francisco), April 3, 1900-July 5, 1900
      - Hale, George E. (Yerkes Observatory), July 17, 1899-Ocotber 18, 1901 (Box 17j, Folder 34)
      - Hartman, T. (Artrophys Observatory, Postsdam), March 19, 1900
      - Hinks, Arthur (The Observatory, Cambridge), June 17, 1903
      - Jacoby, Harold (Astronomical Observatory, Columbia University, New York), January 24, 1900-December 9, 1901 (Box 17j, Folder 35)
      - Jesse, R.H. (University of the State of Missouri, Columbia, MO), April 26, 1901
      - Jordon, David S. (Lelaw Stanford Junior University, Stanford University, CA), December 7, 1901
      - Kreatr, H. (Keil, Germany), September 15, 1901
      - Leuschner, Armin O. (Students Observatory, University of California), March 16, 1900-November 17, 1900 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Liebisch, B. (Leipzig, Germany), August 21, 1900
      - Murdock Press (San Francisco), June 6, 1901
      - Parkherst, John A. (Marengo, IL), December 1, 1899-July 4, 1900
      - Phipps, S.C. (Berkley, CA), April 1, 1900-May 27, 1900
      - Pritchett, Henry Smith (Massachusetts Institute of Technology), March 13, 1900-April 23, 1901
      - Porter, J.S. (Cincinnati Observatory), June 8, 1900
      - Preston, E.D. (Washington, DC), March 14, 1900
      - Rees, J.K. (New York), December 1, 1899-April 7, 1903 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Ritchey, Alfeda (Lake Geneva, WI), December 27, 1901
      - Rogers, A.O. (San Francisco), November 27, 1900
      - Smith, Edwin (US Coast and Geodetic Survey, Washington), January 15, 1900-May 23, 1901 (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Trel, T.R. (Astronomical Society of the Pacific, San Francisco), February 14, 1901-October 26, 1901
      - Townley, Sidney D. (Astronomical Society of the Pacific, Berkley, CA), January 1, 1900-July 6, 1906 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Treasury Department, Office of the Coast and Geodetic Survey, Washington, DC, June 4, 1901
      - Tucker, R.H. (Lick Observatory), January 30, 1900
      - Twitchell, Edward W., January 31, 1900-September 1, 1900
      - U.S. Naval Observatory, Washington, DC, May 9, 1901
      - Wanach, B. (Postscharn, Germany), June 29, 1900
      - Wilczynski, E.J. (Berkley, CA), May 23, 1900-August 11, 1900
      - Williamson, E.B. (Bluffton, Indiana), April 6, 1900
      - Woodward, R.S. (Columbia University), May 20, 1901
    - Personal Correspondence to Schlesinger
      - Camerer, Emile (New York), July 23, 1901 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Davis, Herman (Washington, DC), July 7, 1900; May 1, 1901
      - Flessner, Herman (New York), March 8, 1900
      - Frank, Rose (New York), April 11, 1900; May 30, 1900
      - Horpham, Flora E. (New York), February 9, 1900-March 31, 1902
      - Hirsch, Mabelle, February 8, 1900
      - Jones, Cecil K. (Fowler, CA), May 15, 1900 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Kanser, Edwar (Germany), December 5, 1899; March 30 1901
      - Ling, George H. (Wesleyan University, Middletown, CT), November 5, 1900-September 22, 1901
      - McAdie, Alexander (U.S. Weather Bureau, San Francisco), May 16, 1901 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Miller, C.W. (San Francisco), January 30, 1900-January 26, 1901
      - Mitchell, S.A., March 10, 1901-August 2, 1901
      - Nesbitt, Scott (Washington, DC), May 8, 1901
      - Pritchett, Henry S. (Massachusetts Institute of Technology), May 2, 1901
      - Ritchey, Elfreda L. (Williams Bay, WI), June 12, 1899-May 2, 1901 (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - Rogers, A.O. (San Francisco), January 11, 1900-March 13, 1901
      - Sayuer, Mrs. J. V. (Williams Bay, WI), March 19, 1903
      - Schlesinger, Emanuel and Alice, October 23, 1900-June 16, 1903 (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - Schlesinger, Gus, Arnelia, Gaby and Mignon (New York), May 4, 1900-December 1, 1901
      - Schlesinger, Joe (New York), March 26, 1901
      - Schlesinger, Minnie (New York), June 5, 1903
      - ? (U.S. Naval Observatory), September 29, 1900
      - ? (Observatorie Astronomique G. Metérologique, Lyon, France), March 13, 1901
    - Personal Correspondence from Schlesinger
      - Kirkpatrick, J. B. (New Brunswick, NJ), November 10, 1900 (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - Schlesinger, Minnie. (New York), October 19, 1899
    - Personal Correspondence to Eva Schlesinger and Frank Jr.
      - Davis, Coreita R. (Washington, DC), July 10, 1900 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - Davis, Helen L (Columbia University, New York), c. 1901
      - Harpham, Flora E. (New York), April 30, 1901
      - Hirsch, B.S. [Eva's father], March 13,1900
      - Kayuk, S., April 8, 1901
      - Kelton, Genevieve (Ventura, CA), with enclosure to Frank Jr., April 9, 1901
      - ? [Eva's Grandfather], April 14, 1901
      - ? Sue., April 15, 1901
  - Heber D. Curtis, 1916-1930; 7.
    Heber D. Curtis was Director from 1920-1930. His field of interest was solar eclipses and stellar spectroscopy. He took part in eleven eclipse expeditions, five while he was Director of Allegheny Observatory. Talented in the construction and operation of scientific instruments, he built a machine shop as well as precision instruments. Dr. Curtis left in 1930 to become Director of Observatories of the University of Michigan.
    - Ac-Am (Box 18, Folder 417)
    - Ait (Box 18, Folder 418-419)
    - Alb-Alt (Box 18, Folder 420)
    - Alu-American Association (Box 18, Folder 421)
    - American Association F (Box 18, Folder 422)
    - American Association of American Re (Box 18, Folder 423)
    - American, Re (Box 18, Folder 424-426)
    - American, Ro-Astron (Box 18, Folder 427)
    - Astrop-Bab (Box 18, Folder 428)
    - Bac (Box 18, Folder 429-433)
    - Bai-Ban (Box 18, Folder 434)
    - Bar (Box 18, Folder 435)
    - Bau-Beal (Box 19, Folder 436-440)
    - Bras-Bri (Box 19, Folder 441)
    - Bro-Bry (Box 19, Folder 442)
    - Buf-Bury (Box 19, Folder 443)
    - Burn (Box 19, Folder 444)
    - Burt-Campbell, J (Box 19, Folder 445)
    - Campbell, W (Box 19, Folder 446-449)
    - Car (Box 19, Folder 450)
    - Cha (Box 19, Folder 451)
    - Chi-Coa (Box 19, Folder 452)
    - Col-Com (Box 19, Folder 453)
    - Con-Cox (Box 19, Folder 454)
    - Cr-Cur (Box 19, Folder 455)
    - Cut-Din (Box 19, Folder 456)
    - Cir-Dodd (Box 19, Folder 457)
    - Dodw (Box 19, Folder 458)
    - Dol (Box 19, Folder 459)
    - Dom-Dr (Box 19, Folder 460)
    - Du (Box 19, Folder 461)
    - Ea (Box 19, Folder 462)
    - Ec (Box 19, Folder 463)
    - Ed-Em (Box 19, Folder 464)
    - En-Fa (Box 19, Folder 465)
    - Fe-Fox, M (Box 19, Folder 466)
    - Fox, P (Box 19, Folder 467)
    - Fra (Box 19, Folder 468)
    - Fre-Fu (Box 19, Folder 469)
    - Ga (Box 20, Folder 470)
    - Gi-Go (Box 20, Folder 471)
    - Gr (Box 20, Folder 472)
    - Hah-Ham (Box 20, Folder 473)
    - Har-Has (Box 20, Folder 474)
    - Hau-Hef (Box 20, Folder 475)
    - Hei-Hen (Box 20, Folder 476)
    - Hi-Ho (Box 20, Folder 477)
    - Hu (Box 20, Folder 478)
    - Hy (Box 20, Folder 479)
    - Intel (Box 20, Folder 480-484)
    - Io-Jar (Box 20, Folder 485)
    - Jaf-Ju (Box 20, Folder 486)
    - Ka-Ki (Box 20, Folder 487)
    - Ki-Kn (Box 20, Folder 488)
    - Ko-La (Box 20, Folder 489)
    - Le (Box 20, Folder 490)
    - Lib-Lin (Box 20, Folder 491)
    - Lio-Ll (Box 20, Folder 492)
    - Lo-Lu (Box 20, Folder 493)
    - McA-McDon (Box 20, Folder 494)
    - McDow (Box 20, Folder 495-496)
    - McF-Mac (Box 20, Folder 497)
    - Marr (Box 20, Folder 498)
    - Mars-Mart (Box 20, Folder 499)
    - Mas-Meg (Box 20, Folder 500)
    - Meh-Merria (Box 21, Folder 501)
    - Merril-Mie (Box 21, Folder 502)
    - Mil (Box 21, Folder 503-516)
    - Min-Mit (Box 21, Folder 517)
    - Mit (Box 21, Folder 518-519)
    - Mon-Moo (Box 21, Folder 520)
    - Mor-Nac (Box 21, Folder 521)
    - National, Ac (Box 21, Folder 522)
    - National, AS-National, S (Box 21, Folder 523)
    - Natu-New (Box 21, Folder 524)
    - New, E (Box 21, Folder 525)
    - New, E (Box 22, Folder 526)
    - New, K-O'd (Box 22, Folder 527)
    - Og-Ou (Box 22, Folder 528)
    - Pa (Box 22, Folder 529)
    - Pe (Box 22, Folder 530)
    - Ph-Pitt (Box 22, Folder 531)
    - Pittsburgh (Box 22, Folder 532)
    - Pl-Poo (Box 22, Folder 533)
    - Poo (Box 22, Folder 534)
    - Pop (Box 22, Folder 535)
    - Por-Pu (Box 22, Folder 536)
    - Ra-Re (Box 22, Folder 537)
    - Ri-Rod (Box 22, Folder 538)
    - Rot (Box 22, Folder 539)
    - Roy-Ru (Box 22, Folder 540)
    - Sa-Sch (Box 22, Folder 541)
    - Schl (Box 22, Folder 542-550)
    - Schl (Box 23, Folder 551-556)
    - Science (Box 23, Folder 557)
    - Scient (Box 23, Folder 558)
    - Sch-Shan (Box 23, Folder 559)
    - Shap (Box 23, Folder 560-561)
    - She-Si (Box 23, Folder 562)
    - Sli (Box 23, Folder 563)
    - Slo-Su (Box 23, Folder 564)
    - So-Steb (Box 23, Folder 565)
    - Stec-Steu (Box 23, Folder 566)
    - Sto (Box 23, Folder 567)
    - Stra (Box 23, Folder 568)
    - Stre (Box 23, Folder 569)
    - Sw (Box 23, Folder 570)
    - Sy-Te (Box 23, Folder 571)
    - Tha (Box 23, Folder 572-574)
    - Th-Thi (Box 23, Folder 575)
    - Tho-Tr (Box 24, Folder 576)
    - Tu-United, P (Box 24, Folder 577)
    - U.S., B-U.S., C (Box 24, Folder 578)
    - U.S., G-U.S., N (Box 24, Folder 579)
    - U.S., R-Van, M (Box 24, Folder 580)
    - Van, R (Box 24, Folder 581)
    - Vas-Ve (Box 24, Folder 582)
    - Vo-Ward (Box 24, Folder 583)
    - Warn-Weste (Box 24, Folder 584)
    - Westi (Box 24, Folder 585)
    - Wh-Wra (Box 24, Folder 586)
    - Wri (Box 24, Folder 587-589)
    - Ya-Yr (Box 24, Folder 590)
    - Yw-Yu (Box 24, Folder 591)
    - University of Pittsburgh, A-Bus (Box 24, Folder 592)
    - University of Pittsburgh, Bus (Box 24, Folder 593-598)
    - University of Pittsburgh, Bud-Cat (Box 24, Folder 599)
    - University of Pittsburgh, Cha (Box 24, Folder 600)
    - University of Pittsburgh, Cha (Box 25, Folder 601)
    - University of Pittsburgh, Cha-Chi (Box 25, Folder 602)
    - University of Pittsburgh, D. (Box 25, Folder 603)
    - University of Pittsburgh, E-G (Box 25, Folder 604)
    - University of Pittsburgh, H-K (Box 25, Folder 605)
    - University of Pittsburgh, M-Seco (Box 25, Folder 606)
    - University of Pittsburgh, Secr (Box 25, Folder 607-611)
    - University of Pittsburgh, Si-Su (Box 25, Folder 612)
    - University of Pittsburgh, T-Z (Box 25, Folder 613)
  - Frank C. Jordan, 1908-1941; 8.
    Frank Craig Jordan was Director from 1930-1941. Jordan worked with Frank Schlesinger at Yerkes and in 1908 followed him to Allegheny Observatory and continued Schlesinger's programs, including parallax methods. Dr. Jordan made outstanding contributions in the endeavor of photographic photometry of variable stars. He died in a house fire in 1941.
    - Ai-A (Box 25, Folder 614)
    - Ar-As (Box 25, Folder 615)
    - Au-B (Box 25, Folder 616)
    - Ca-Co (Box 25, Folder 617)
    - Cr-Cu (Box 25, Folder 618)
    - Do-Ea (Box 25, Folder 619)
    - Eb-Hi (Box 25, Folder 620)
    - Ho-K (Box 25, Folder 621)
    - L-Me (Box 25, Folder 622)
    - Mi-O (Box 25, Folder 623)
    - P (Box 25, Folder 624)
    - R (Box 25, Folder 625)
    - Sch (Box 26, Folder 626-628)
    - Sh-Su (Box 26, Folder 629)
    - T-Wa (Box 26, Folder 630)
    - We-V (Box 26, Folder 631)
    - University of Pittsburgh (Box 26, Folder 632)
    - New Material Added, 2013
      - Jordan - Parkhurst Correspondence, 1908 (Box 74, Folder 1)
  - Nicholas E. Wagman, 1930-1970; 9.
    Nicholas Emory Wagman was Acting Director from 1941-1947, then Director from 1947-1970. Wagman became an astronomer at the Observatory in 1930 and became acting director in 1941 upon Dr. Jordan's death. In 1946 he announced one of the rarest finds of modern astronomy: a dark star in the constellation Ophiucus, which he named "Alpha Opiuchi C." As a result of this discovery, he was appointed Director in 1947. He investigated stellar and astrometric binaries and undertook a comprehensive program of modernization. He played a leading role in the disseminating of information on astronomy to the Pittsburgh public community. He served as lecturer at Buhl Planetarium and conducted forums at the YMCA. He was prominent as a member of the American Astronomical Society and the American Association for the Advancement of Science. He left the Allegheny Observatory in 1970.
    - Ab-Ad (Box 74, Folder 633)
    - All (Box 74, Folder 634-635)
    - All-Alp (Box 74, Folder 636)
    - Ama (Box 74, Folder 637-640)
    - American, A-American, M (Box 74, Folder 641)
    - An-Ar (Box 74, Folder 642)
    - As (Box 74, Folder 643)
    - Av-Bea (Box 74, Folder 644)
    - Ber-Bil (Box 74, Folder 645)
    - Bin (Box 74, Folder 646)
    - Bl-Bra (Box 74, Folder 647)
    - Bro (Box 74, Folder 648)
    - Bru-Buh (Box 74, Folder 649)
    - By-Cal (Box 74, Folder 650)
    - Cam-Clu (Box 27, Folder 651)
    - Clu (Box 27, Folder 652)
    - Coh-Com (Box 27, Folder 653)
    - Coo-Cu (Box 27, Folder 654)
    - Dan (Box 27, Folder 655)
    - Dav (Box 27, Folder 656)
    - De-Do (Box 27, Folder 657)
    - Dr-Ea (Box 27, Folder 658)
    - Eb (Box 27, Folder 659-660)
    - Ed-Eu (Box 27, Folder 661)
    - Fe-Fl (Box 27, Folder 662)
    - Fo-Gan (Box 27, Folder 663)
    - Ga (Box 27, Folder 664)
    - Ge-Go (Box 27, Folder 665)
    - Gre-Gri (Box 27, Folder 666)
    - Ha-Heb (Box 27, Folder 667)
    - Hei-Her (Box 27, Folder 668)
    - Hey-Ho (Box 27, Folder 669)
    - Hu-Hy (Box 27, Folder 670)
    - I-J (Box 27, Folder 671)
    - Ka (Box 27, Folder 672)
    - Ke-Kl (Box 27, Folder 673)
    - Ko-Ku (Box 27, Folder 674)
    - La-Le (Box 27, Folder 675)
    - Li-Lu (Box 28, Folder 676)
    - Ma-McD (Box 28, Folder 677)
    - Mc-Mrc (Box 28, Folder 678)
    - Mid-Mu (Box 28, Folder 679)
    - Mu (Box 28, Folder 680)
    - Mas-Natl (Box 28, Folder 681)
    - Nati (Box 28, Folder 682-684)
    - Natu-Ne (Box 28, Folder 685)
    - No (Box 28, Folder 686)
    - Pa-Pe (Box 28, Folder 687)
    - Pec-Pi (Box 28, Folder 688)
    - Po-Pre (Box 28, Folder 689)
    - Pri-Ra (Box 28, Folder 690)
    - Re-Ri (Box 28, Folder 691)
    - Ro (Box 28, Folder 692)
    - Sa-Scho (Box 28, Folder 693)
    - Schl-Schw (Box 28, Folder 694)
    - Schw-Shar (Box 28, Folder 695)
    - Shaw-Shi (Box 28, Folder 696)
    - Sho-Sk (Box 28, Folder 697)
    - Sm-So (Box 28, Folder 698)
    - Sp-Ste (Box 28, Folder 699)
    - Stu (Box 28, Folder 700)
    - Str (Box 29, Folder 701)
    - Stu-Swa (Box 29, Folder 702)
    - Swe-Ta (Box 29, Folder 703)
    - Te-U (Box 29, Folder 704)
    - Vae-Van, B (Box 29, Folder 705)
    - Van, D (Box 29, Folder 706-708)
    - Van, P-Vas (Box 29, Folder 709)
    - Ve-Wa (Box 29, Folder 710)
    - Wee-Westi (Box 29, Folder 711)
    - Westo (Box 29, Folder 712)
    - Wh-Will (Box 29, Folder 713)
    - Wils (Box 29, Folder 714)
    - Win-Wu (Box 29, Folder 715)
    - Wy-Yo (Box 29, Folder 716)
    - University of Pittsburgh, B-Ch (Box 29, Folder 717)
    - University of Pittsburgh, Cr (Box 29, Folder 718-721)
    - University of Pittsburgh, H (Box 29, Folder 722)
    - University of Pittsburgh, L (Box 29, Folder 723)
    - University of Pittsburgh, O-P (Box 29, Folder 724)
    - University of Pittsburgh, V (Box 29, Folder 725)
    - New Material Added, 2013
      - Wagman Correspondence (Box 74, Folder 2-5)
      - Wagman Correspondence - Other and University (Box 74, Folder 6)
  - Joost H. Kiewiet de Jonge, 1953-1977; 10.
    - Kiewiet de Jonge Correspondence (Box 74, Folder 7-13)
    - Kiewiet de Jonge Correspondence - University Correspondence (Box 74, Folder 14-15)
- Letterpress Books of Directors/Acting Directors, 1862-1910; II.
  As with the correspondence of the Directors/Acting Directors, the letterpress books of the Directors/Acting Directors have also been microfilmed and a detailed item listing can be found in Indexes to the Microfilmed Correspondence of Directors/Acting Directors and selected Astronomers Among the Records of the Allegheny Observatory. There are four books, however, that are not indexed in that inventory. The first, a letterpress book of F.L.O. Wadsworth, has not been microfilmed or indexed. This book is in Box 33. The remaining three in Box 34 are from Frank Schlesinger and were microfilmed separately as AIS.1981.06. Indexes appear at the end of each volume and indexes to all three Schlesinger letterpress books can be found at the beginning of reel 1 of AIS.1981.06 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9).
  - Samuel Pierpont Langley, 1884-1889; 1.
    Samuel Pierpont Langley was the first Director of the Allegheny Observatory and held that position from 1867 to 1887. His primary interest was the sun and he began his studies of the sun immediately after assuming the post of Director. Langley prepared drawings of sun spots and associated phenomena and astronomers, today, are still familiar with Langley's classic drawing of the great sunspot of 1873.
    In 1869 Langley devised and made operational the electric system of transmitting telegraphic time to several of the Pennsylvania Railroad lines which were associated with the observatory. In the area of magnetic disturbances, Langley was the first to associate such disturbances on the earth with solar outbreaks of an extremely active character.
    Concerning studies in the realm of solar physics, Professor Langley was impressed with the idea that much radiant energy from the sun could not be recognized with instruments then in use, and after much experimentation, he invented the bolometer. With this instrument he succeeded in measuring the amount of heat radiation on the earth from the sun (the solar constant).
    Professor Langley studied many minor though important questions concerning radiant energy. His investigations of the moon's temperature added greatly to our knowledge of the moon. Langley used his spectrobolometer to measure the highest temperature of the moon which was found to be approximately zero degrees centigrade and the lowest temperature of the moon which was found to be equivalent to the temperature of space.
    Langley also collected data on the part of the solar system beyond the infra-red zone. With the aid of Professors Keeler, Very, and Page measurements were made by Langley utilizing the spectrobolometer and the galvanometer which he invented before photographic methods were develop.
    Langley, of course, has received much recognition for his contributions to aeronautics. However, his original intention was not to construct a flying-machine, but instead to "determine the laws governing flight." At the Allegheny Observatory, Langley built a whirling arm on which "he tested airfoils, fusiforms and other aerodynamic objects, measuring their angels and pressures as they moved through the air at varying speeds." Studies of actual birds and "mechanical birds" ("winged contrivance" made of tin, cork, and rubber) were conducted and findings published in a paper entitled "Experiments in Aerodynamics."
    Professor Langley left his post at the Allegheny Observatory in 1887 (leaving F.W. Very, his assistant, in charge) to become Assistant Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution; later, following the death of Professor Baird, he was elected Secretary of the Institution in 1891. Langley continued his research in aerodynamics and from a catapult, on May 6, 1896, launched an unmanned, steam-powered flying machine over the Potomac. It flew more than a half mile and was subsequently recovered. The first manned flight of his gasoline-powered "aerodome" failed in 1903 because of a launching device defect. Glenn Curtiss successfully piloted Langley's restored plane eight years after his death.
    Note: Calendar entries covering the period 1884-1889 (Letterpress books no.'s I, II, and III) consist of abstracts of letters selected from four areas of research: 1) magnetic disturbances, 2) solar radiation, 3) mapping of infra-red spectrum, and 4) aerodynamics. There are also selected abstracts relating to both the electric time signal service and miscellaneous correspondence.
    Please note that references to pagination indicate number of pages letters occupy in letterpress books and not necessarily number of pages of actual letters.
    - Samuel Langley, 1862-1872 (Box 30, Volume 1)
    - Samuel Langley, 1884-1887 (Box 30, Volume 2)
      Scope and Contents note
      This calendar, comprised of Volumes 2-3, was prepared by David Lieberman, a student in the Graduate School of Library and Information Sciences, University of Pittsburgh, as an independent study project during September - December, 1973.
      - Reed, J.R. Pittsburgh, PA Comparative bolometer measurement to determine bolometer efficiency, 2p., March 6, 1884; 1.